Finding Aid for the Alan Engebretsen Papers Biomed.1246
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alan C. Engebretsen papers
1964-2010
UCLA Library Special Collections
Engebretsen, Alan C., 1947-2019
Hollenbach, Margaret (Molly)
Biomed.1246
17.2 linear feet (38 boxes)
Alan C. Engebretsen was a virtually unknown poet from California. Engebretsen was diagnosed with, and treated for paranoid schizophrenia for most of his adult life, beginning during military service in his 20s. The collection contains lecture notes, notes on reading in psychology and psychiatry, poems that were prepared or submitted for publication, diaries, letters, and activity logs. The bulk of the collection consists of decades' worth of poems written by the author.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret (Molly) Hollenbach, 2023.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9997060633306533
Biographical History
Alan C. Engebretsen (3 January 1947 - 8 July 2019) was a virtually unknown poet from California who graduated high school in 1964 and died in 2019 at age 72.
Engebretsen was diagnosed with, and treated for paranoid schizophrenia for most of his adult life, beginning during military service in his 20s. He was a fluent, gifted writer and wrote poetry daily. He also kept many detailed logs of his thoughts on what he read, or heard on the radio, and other commonplace diaries/logs; many, like his poems, are dated and line-counted throughout. Alan edited and published a small poetry journal for two years and had minor success publishing his own work elsewhere (Amelia, California State Poetry Quarterly, Orphic Lute, Proof Rock, Prophetic Voices, Pudding Magazine, Wind). He left one self-published collection under his own imprint: "A Rage of Blue: Poems New and Used" (Poetic Justice Press, 1985; 48 pp.).
Source: Biography by donor, Margaret Hollenbach, and curator, Russell Johnson, 2023.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains notes and papers for Engebretsen's psychology courses, presumably from college classes; notes on reading in psychology and psychiatry; and poems that were prepared or submitted for publication and some which were successfully published through the author's imprint (Poetic Justice Press) or by others. The bulk of the collection consists of decades' worth of poems written by the author on lined loose-leaf paper or typed on unlined paper, dated-stamped and line-counted; spiral-bound notebooks serving as commonplace books of poems, thoughts, notes on reading and lectures attended, and letters; daybook, diary, and activity logs; notes and quotations about single-word concepts; pocket-size spiral notebooks with notes on readings; and daily activity and thought logs for the author's last decade.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged by types of materials and then further organized chornologically.
Poetry; Poets, American -- 20th century -- Archives; Hollenbach, Margaret (Molly); Engebretsen, Alan C., 1947-2019 -- Archives
- Biographical materials, 1964; 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folders 1-2)
- Prose manuscripts, 1970-1987 (Box 1, Folders 3-7)
- Academic materials, 1970-1987 (Box 1, Folders 8-17, Box 2, Folder 1-6)
- Poems Engebretsen read in public, submitted for publication, or published, 1965-1990 (Box 2, Folders 7-17, Box 3, Folder 1-13)
- Poems, 1965-2009
  Scope and Contents
  Manuscripts on lined looseleaf paper and typescripts on unlined white paper; date-stamped; many with line counts.
  - Poems, 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folders 14-18, Box 4, Folders 1-22, Box 5, Folders 1-5, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Poems, 1972-1983 (Box 6, Folders 2-17, Box 7, Folders 1-10, Box 8)
  - Poems, 1986-1995 (Box 9, Folder 1-10, Box 10, Folders 1-8, Box 11, Folders 1-7)
  - Poems, 1996-1999 (Box 11, Folder 8, Box 12, Folders 1-7, Box 13, Folders 1-10, Box 14)
  - Poems, 2000-2002 (Box 14, Folders 7-10, Box 15, Folders 1-7, Box 16, Folders 1-8)
  - Poems, 2003-2006 (Box 16, Folder 9, Box 17, Folders 1-9, Box 18, Folders 1-7)
  - Poems, 2006-2009 (Box 19, Folders 1-8, Box 20, Folders 1-9, Box 21, Folders 1-3)
- Commonplace books of poems, thoughts, notes on reading and lectures attended, and letters, 1966-1980 (Box 21, Folders 4-9, Box 22, Folders 1-9, Box 23, Folders 1-6)
  Spiral notebooks with lined paper; some with AEC's title page, named for the color of the cover.
- Daybook, diary, and activity logs, 1977-2010 (Box 23, Folders 7-8, Box 24, Folders 1-6, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Folders 1-7, Box 31, Box 32, Folders 1-5)
  Spiral notebooks with lined paper, with dated entries.
- Notes and quotations about single-word concepts, 2002-2006 (Box 32, Folder 6, Box 33, Folders 1-6, Box 34, Folders 1-10)
  Composition notebooks with lined paper, collecting notes and quotes about change, creativity, education, teachers, honesty, knowledge, learning, love, and power.
- Notebooks with notes on reading, 1968-2009 (Box 35, Folders 1-7, Box 36, Folders 1-6, Box 37, Folders 1-5, Box 38)
  Pocket-size spiral notebooks with lined paper, with dated entries.